Guide to the Christopher Cox Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Christopher Cox papers
1927-1990
1966-1990
YCAL MSS 264
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.73
(47 boxes)
The Christopher Cox Papers consists of the writings, correspondence files, and personal papers of the editor, author, actor, director, and producer Christopher Cox, and of his partner, the art historian William Olander.
Cox, Christopher, 1949-1990
Olander, William
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Nancy Cox, 1993 and 1994.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 47 (audiocassettes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 47 (computer disk): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Christopher Cox (1949-1990)
Christopher Cox (1949-1990), an editor, author, actor, director, and producer, was born August 27, 1949, in Gadsden, Alabama, to Howard R. Cox, a prominent banker, and Dorothy Trusler Cox. His birth name was Howard Raymond Cox Jr., and his family and childhood friends called him Ray throughout his life. He graduated from Emma Sansom High School, as did his brother Timothy, and sisters Carol and Nancy.
In 1966, at age 16, Cox took a summer job in Washington as a page for Alabama's senator John Sparkman, and then returned to the city the summer after high school to work for two representatives, Armistead Selden and George Andrews. He attended the University of Alabama in Birmingham for two years, where he became involved in college dramatics. Dropping out at the end of his sophomore year, Cox moved to New York in hopes of a career in the theatre and never returned to college (although he did list a 1969 BA from the University of Alabama on some of his resumes). His first role was an understudy for the Mute in The Fantasticks, which he said was the only role open to him because of his Southern accent. It is not clear whether he achieved further study in theater, but ephemera in Series III, Personal Papers, indicates that he took classes at the HB Studio in New York in the fall of 1969.
Cox took Christopher as his professional name in 1970, he wrote to his friend Steven Beil, because when he went to join the Actors' Equity labor union there was a Ray Cox already enrolled. His life in the theatre included performing, directing, and writing both plays and lyrics. His primary contribution was as director of the New Play Series and the Writers Workshop at the Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company, where he produced a dozen works by young playwrights between 1974 and 1976. He performed in both Broadway and Off-Broadway shows through the 1970s before turning more to writing, editing, and photography in the 1980s. In the last decade of his life, Cox worked for publishing houses, primarily E.P. Dutton and Ballantine, and wrote freelance articles and reviews for the Soho Weekly News (published between 1974 and 1982) and other papers and magazines. His book, A Key West Companion, was issued by St. Martin's Press in 1983, and his short study of photographer Dorothea Lange was published by Aperture in 1987.
Cox was affiliated with a literary group known as the Violet Quill (or, as he wrote in his diary on March 31, 1980, the Lavender Quill), whose seven members, men writing for men, are regarded as one of the strongest collective voices of the gay male experience in the post-Stonewall era. Authors Robert Ferro, Michael Grumley, Andrew Holleran, Felice Picano, Edmund White, George Whitmore, and Cox, met several times in 1979, 1980, and 1981 to read aloud from and discuss their works in progress, as well as those by their friends. Also on their agenda were discussions of how they could work together to promote recognition, acceptance, and publication of gay literature beyond the boundaries of their own community. Within ten years Ferro, Grumley, and Whitmore had died from AIDS-related complications, as did Christopher Cox on September 7, 1990. He was 41 years of age.
Though he left Alabama in 1969, the place and the people were never far from Cox's mind, and both regularly appear as central motifs in his stories. The early deaths of his uncle Roy (by suicide in 1956) and his mother (from cancer in 1975) were also significant events in his life and became focal points in his writings. One important job that Cox held was as a secretary to composer Virgil Thomson, from March 1975 through 1977. In his position, he arranged and cataloged Thomson's correspondence and music manuscripts prior to their transfer to Yale University; in turn, the job gave him immediate access to the people in Thomson's circle, and to his neighbors in the Chelsea Hotel where Cox would eventually live as well. Thomson composed his portrait, "Christopher Cox: Singing a Song," in 1981.
In his script for "Neurotic Moon," a 1978 video piece, Cox described the job of Christopher, his main character, as a secretary for "an old, established and famous composer assembling the man's correspondence and musical manuscripts for donation to a large library." About Christopher, he wrote, "What he is doing is putting together the pieces of this man's life while his life is falling to pieces." The number of semi-autobiographical (and outright autobiographical) writings that Christopher Cox left at his death, nearly all of which were incomplete and unpublished, reveal that though many pieces of his life were complex and difficult, they were also an asset as a resource from which he drew to write openly about the gay community, as well as the world he left behind in the South.
William R. Olander (1950-1989)
William R. Olander (1950-1989), the partner of Christopher Cox, was an art historian, museum curator, and critic. Born in Virginia, Minnesota, on July 14, 1950, he attended Northwestern University, where he studied with Jack Burnham, and received a Ph.D. in art history from New York University's Institute of Fine Arts in 1983. His dissertation, Pour Transmettre À La Postérité: French Painting and Revolution, 1774-1795, was guided by the noted art historian Robert Rosenblum. After internships at the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Toledo Museum of Art, Olander was appointed curator of modern art at the Allen Memorial Museum at Oberlin College; he held that position from 1979 to 1984, and served as the museum's acting director in his last two years there. On January 1, 1985, he became curator at the New Museum of Contemporary Art in New York, and met Christopher Cox in the spring of 1986. Olander was senior curator at the New Museum when he died from AIDS-related complications on March 18, 1989. An obituary and papers related his memorial service and the William Olander Fund at the New Museum are in Series I, Box 5, folder 113.
In addition to organizing exhibitions at both museums during his years there, Olander served as a guest curator, juror, or catalogue essayist for shows in many other venues. Among his exhibitions were the Allen Memorial Museum's New Voices series: 6 Photographers (1981) and Women and the Media: New Video (1984); Drawings: After Photography (circulated by Independent Curators Incorporated, 1984); Fake (The New Museum, 1987); and retrospectives of the work of artists May Stevens (New Museum, 1988), Edgar Franceschi (El Museo Del Barrio, 1988), and Janet Cooling (Beacon Street Gallery, Chicago, 1989). He wrote, as well, numerous exhibition and book reviews, and presented papers at academic institutions and conferences on the topics of French painting, new media, photography, and postmodern theory. Particularly interested the work of women and other marginalized artists, Olander often incorporated social and political statements, performance art, video, film, and photography into his exhibition programs.
William Olander is probably best remembered for his activist work within the art world, particularly for his invitation to the collectivist organization ACT UP/NY (AIDS Coalition to Unleash Power, New York) to fill the main show window of the New Museum's building at 583 Broadway. Unveiled on November 20, 1987, the landmark installation is known as "Let the Record Show…," after Olander's statement in the accompanying brochure: "Let the record show that there are many in the community of art and artists who chose not to be silent in the 1980s." The display incorporated a bold neon sign stating "SILENCE = DEATH," which brought the group's slogan to a wider public awareness.
Scope and Contents
The Christopher Cox Papers consists of the writings, correspondence files, and personal papers of the writer, director, and producer Christopher Cox, and of his partner, the art historian William Olander. A typed list titled "File Cabinets (Drawers Needed)," now in the Series III folder Miscellaneous notes (Box 23, Folder 402) suggests Cox's home office filing arrangement and takes into account a large part of the material now present in the collection: Cox's correspondence files; personal and family papers spanning his lifetime; his writings and theatrical work; and documentation of the positions he held with Virgil Thomson and the Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company. The list also reveals that what is not present in the collection are the accomplishments for which he is most noted: there are no files for his book A Key West Companion (1983); there only two examples of his published articles; and there is little evidence of his career as a photographer beyond a folder of photo orders (Box 10, Folder 205) and the credited images that appear in publications of authors such as Edmund White. However, with its highly descriptive homoerotic writings and visual material, the collection is a rich primary source for chronicling gay culture, lifestyles, and literature in New York during the 1970s and 1980s, as well as Off Off-Broadway theatre in the 1970s.
Perhaps as a holdover from his time as a secretary to Virgil Thomson, Cox kept most of his papers neatly filed in manila folders, many with typed paper labels. This is particularly true for the pre-1983 material; for years afterward, most of the papers and correspondence were not in any discernable order, and were not received in file folders. For the most part, Cox's file titles have been retained, though the current series arrangement was instituted when the collection was processed in 2007.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into eight series: Series I. Correspondence (1963-1990, undated); Series II. Creative Work (1969-1989, undated); Series III. Personal Papers (1935-1990, undated); Series IV. Virgil Thomson Files (1947-1984, undated); Series V. Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company Files (1965-1978, undated); Series VI. Subject Files (1927-1989, undated); Series VII. Writings of Others (circa 1949-1987, undated); and Series VIII. William Olander Papers (1968-1989, undated).
American fiction -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Gay men -- Fiction; Gay men -- Sexual behavior; Gay men -- United States; Gay men's writings, American; Sadomasochism; Sex -- New York (State); Violet Quill (Group of writers); Amazon River -- Description and travel; Japan -- Description and travel; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Diaries -- United States -- New York; Electronic documents; Guidebooks; Money; Scripts (documents); Sound recordings; Theatre programs -- United States -- New York; Authors; Museum curators; LGBTQ resource; Busby, Gerald; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Corn, Alfred, 1943-; Cox, Christopher, 1949-1990; Dowell, Coleman, 1925-; Grosser, Maurice, 1903-1986; McClatchy, J. D., 1945-; Morris, George, 1943-; Nabokov, Nicolas, 1903-1978; Olander, William; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946; Thomson, Virgil, 1896-1989; Toklas, Alice B., 1877-1967; White, Edmund, 1940-; Yonemoto, Bruce, 1949-; Yonemoto, Norman, 1946-2014; Cox family; Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company
- Correspondence, 1963-1990, undated; Series I; 4.17; (10 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically, followed by general correspondence filed chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. holds letters, both personal and professional, from friends, colleagues, and lovers. It is arranged alphabetically by correspondent, with set of chronologically arranged single letters grouped at the end. There are multiple folders for three of Cox's former lovers, Bob McDonald, George Morris, and Edmund White, and within them are also a few outgoing letters (some just drafts) from Cox. The letters in Series I were primarily sent to Cox, but in the late 1970s, many were addressed both to Cox and White as a couple. Additional letters to Cox appear in other series in the collection: Series III Personal Papers holds all material, including correspondence, connected to Cox's family, and there are a few letters filed in with his "Journal Notes" in Box 21; letters to and from Virgil Thomson are filed in Series IV; and correspondence relating to Cox's work with the Joseph Jefferson Theatre Company is filed in Series V.
  There are some business letters, both to and from Cox and his employers, in the series, though most of the letters are personal in nature. Many of his colleagues at periodicals and publishers, such as the editor Ashton Applewhite, remained in contact with him after their professional involvements ended, and it is clear from their letters they were fond of him even when they could not assist him professionally. Generally speaking, the correspondents were connected to Cox through his publishing and theatre ventures, though some were very intimate friends and acquaintances and their letters, such as those written by Kenneth Locklear, an inmate in a North Carolina prison, contain explicit sexual suggestions and descriptions. At the other end of the scale is the folder for E.P. Dutton, which holds a long strip of paper on which his officemates wrote farewell notes when Cox left the company in September 1983.
  In addition to Virgil Thomson, Cox also worked briefly for Nicholas Nabokov just before the composer's death. His folder holds letters from Nabokov to others. Most of the letters have a draft in Cox's hand (likely a dictation) with a typed carbon; there is one draft in Nabokov's hand.
  The four folders of letters from George Morris were mostly written during the summer of 1977, when he was living in New York City and Cox was in Paris with Virgil Thomson. A native Texan, Morris (born in 1943, died of AIDS in 1989) reviewed films for the Village Voice, among other publications, but eventually settled in Austin and became an influential critic, mentor, and leader in that city's film community. His letters to Cox functioned as almost daily reports and closely document Morris's activities in New York, including accounts of his movie-going experiences.
  There are several folders of papers relating to Edmund White that include both correspondence and some of his writings. The first has letters to Cox, with a few from Cox filed in. The second holds letters written specifically to and from White and John Barth, Joyce Baronio, Kay Boyle, Alfred Corn, and Vera Nabokov, dating from 1978-1979. Cox kept all White's letters and writings together, as opposed to separating the letters and writings of other authors, most likely because his relationship with White was so deeply personal and meaningful. That arrangement has been retained here. One folder with White's miscellaneous writings has a photocopy of the typescript of his essay "Nabokov: Beyond Parody" (1983), a manuscript of an untitled essay on Roland Barthes, a carbon typescript of a review of Ivan Morris's book The Nobility of Failure (1975), and an edited carbon typescript of the first chapter of his novel, A Boy's Own Story (1982). The two folders for White's books have reviews, dust jackets, invitations, and profiles of the author, which also include photographs of White taken by Christopher Cox. Reviews for Nocturnes for the King of Naples include a letter from Cox to the editor of The Advocate disputing a poor review the book received from the paper's literary critic.
  At the end of the series is miscellaneous correspondence, such as cards, letters, and mass mailings, that were kept by Cox in a set of files that he had created and labeled "General Correspondence," "Employment," and "Photography." These chronological files hold single letters, notes, and birthday and holiday cards from friends and colleagues (those from his family are filed in Series III, Personal Papers with other family correspondence). During processing, additional files were created to separate out mass mailings sent to Cox from organizations of which he was a member, such as the New York City Ballet, or where his name appeared on a distribution list, such as commercial art galleries and clubs.
  - Actors' Equity Association, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - The Advocate, 1978-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alabama Inaugural Committee, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alfred A. Knopf Incorporated, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Altman, Leonard, 1977-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Poetry Review, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Anderson, Dennis, 1973-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Andre Deutsch, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Aperture, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Applewhite, Ashton, 1981-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: St. Martin's Press
  - Artists' TV Lab, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Avedon, Richard, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Averill, Brett, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Barker, Fran, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Baronio, Joyce, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Beil, Steven R., 1968-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bettis Schmidt, Valerie, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bietrix, Bernard, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bishop, Robert
    See: Engel, Lehman
  - Book Digest, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Boylan, Mary, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Brainard, Joe, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Brook, Peter, 1973, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Busby, Gerald, 1979-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Byers, Sam
    See: Busby, Gerald
  - Cardell, Victor, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Cartier, Xam, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Casa-Fuerte, Yvonne de, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Charles, Price of Wales, 1965 Aug 16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Cicero, Louis T., 1976-1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Condé Nast's Traveler, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Cooper, Dennis, 1980-1987 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Copland, Aaron, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Corn, Alfred, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Creative Artists Public Service Program, 1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Daniel, Tamara, 1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Davis, Ken, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - DeJohn, Paul, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Departures, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Diamond, David, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Includes sheet music for "Christmas Tree," with lyrics by E. E. Cummings; dedicated to James Sibley Watson Jr.
  - Djerassi Foundation, 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Dolin, Anton, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Donadio, Candida, 1984-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    See also: Strong, Jonathan
  - Dorn, Margaret
    - Letters, 1973-1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Includes apartment keys
    - Songs, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Dowell, Coleman, 1979-1987 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dunnock, Mildred, 1970 Jul 26 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - DuPont, Louis, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - E.P. Dutton, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Elias, Alix, 1972-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Engel, Lehman, 1971-1975, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Equi, Elaine, 1981, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Farrar, Straus & Giroux, 1980-1986, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    See also: Myles, Eileen
  - Ferro, Robert, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Foye, Raymond, 1983, 1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - France, Richard, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Fried, Rosie, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Frissell, Robert
    See: McDonald, Robert (Bob)
  - Gazette (Montreal), 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Gentleman's Quarterly, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Glazier, Sidney, 1976-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Gorman, Madeleine, 1976, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Gray, Robert, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Groffsky, Maxine, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Gruenau, Douglas, 1979-1985, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Grumley, Michael
    See: Ferro, Robert
  - Halpern, Sue, 1982 Aug (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Holliday, David, 1971-1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Hopkins, Thomas, 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Horwin, Lee, 1971-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Huguley, Robert, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Kelly, Jack, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Institute for Art and Urban Resources, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - International Creative Management, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Jackson, David, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Kennedy, John F. [Evelyn Lincoln], 1963 Sep 9 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Laccetti, Ray, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Levitt, Sandy, 1977, 1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    See also: Linderman, Edward
  - Linderman, Edward, 1973-1980, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Little, Brown & Company, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Livingston, Robert L., 1978 Oct 26 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Locklear, Kenneth, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Lopez-Cepero, Luis, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Lynch, Charles, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - McClatchy, J. D., 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - McDonald, Robert (Bob)
    - Letters and cards, 1969-1978 (Box 3, Folder 84-85)
    - Letters and cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
    - Portrait photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - MacGregor, Trish, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 89)
    See also: Astrology chart and notes
    See also: Brazil, Colombia and Peru (Amazon), and Colombia
  - McKee, Michael, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - McNiven, Roger, 1977-1983 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Manet, Eduardo, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Marshall, Scott
    See: McNiven, Roger
  - Matheson, Paull, 1968-1974, undated (Box 4, Folder 93)
  - Merrill, James, 1980 Mar 1 (Box 4, Folder 94)
  - Miller, Tom
    See: France, Richard
  - Modern Times, 1983, undated (Box 4, Folder 95)
  - Morouse, Denny
    See: Dorn, Margaret
  - Morris, George
    - Letters, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 96-99)
    - Manuscripts, undated (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Clippings, notes, and reviews, 1975-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Reviews in Texas Monthly, 1975-1980 (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Moss, Robert
    See: Anderson, Dennis
    See: Playwrights Horizons
  - Muellerleile, Marianne, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 103)
  - Myles, Eileen, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Nabokov, Dominique, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Nabokov, Nicholas, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 106)
    Includes letters to Peter Brook, John Gross, John Hunt, Theodor Kollek, Peter Mennin, Vera Nabokov, Klaus Piper, Peter Quennell, Michael Smoira-Cohn, Sir Georg Solti, Shepard Stone, Ulrike Tenbrock, and Harry Woolf.
  - Neely, Jim, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Nelson, Craig Richard, 1973-1976 (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - New York Foundation for the Arts, 1984-1985 (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Nichols, Diana and Jack, 1976-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Noojin, Balpha, 1968-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Nurock, Kirk, 1975-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Olander, William, 1987, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 113)
  - Ozick, Cynthia, 1982 Dec 28 (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Parker, Don, 1973-1976, undated (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Payen, Marc, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 116)
  - Pedneau, Dave, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Plant, Richard, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 118)